[Music]
on the surface Douglas Murray's recent
bestseller the strange death of Europe
was a reaction to the migrant crisis of
2015 where he spent months Europe's
borders interviewing migrants natives
and policy makers but in it he argues
that the migrant crisis and Europeans
reaction to it is another symptom of a
broader spiritual crisis a crisis of
meaning and a sense that the story has
run out at a fundamental level well
strange death of Europe was a impart a
response to migration crisis of 2015
pomme words which I saw up close and it
was an attempt by me to meditate on what
I thought was going on through reporting
sort of real-time history writing and
also some philosophizing about the
deeper reasons why it was going on I
wanted to take the opportunity to not
just describe events but describe why
those events might be happening and to
take a step back from what was front
page news every day and saying why was
it why was it happening and I thought
that they were broadly speaking two
components one was the the world
appearing to want to come to Europe and
the other was what had happened in
Europe the men that this was the case
what was it about us that meant for good
and ill that that was going to be
allowed and possible and I wanted to I
wanted to try to address those the
deeper tones because I thought they were
everywhere you couldn't stand borders of
various European countries and not think
of history all the time there is
something about Europe because we've
been a crucible of
considerable amount of civilization for
a long time now that means that every or
a lot of places positively harmony with
history and things that have been
extraordinary and great and things that
have been worse than anything that ever
anyone ever came up with and you draw a
link in that book between a sort of
religious crisis in Europe that we've
lost our values and immigration which is
something that people don't like people
don't like yeah I noticed that could you
explain how this piece is dealing
together well broadly speaking because
we like to think that everybody in the
world is like us which among other
things is somewhat presumptuous and from
a lot of travel in a lot of places over
a lot of years now I come to conclusion
there are enormous number of things that
unite people across the whole world but
there's an awful lot of difference as
well and it isn't just the case that
we're all after the same things or we
all believe the same things it's it's
not the case that we all have the same
views or could have the same views or
should have the same views and it's not
obvious at all to me that if you walk
into another continent even if you
become a citizen that you inevitably
become as much of that continent as
anyone else who's ever been there and it
seems to me that numbers matter and
speed matters and there are a whole set
of very obvious demonstrations of that
and I don't blame individual migrants or
groups of migrants for that but if we
were to transplant an entire Welsh
mining village to Kashmir you would not
expect that village to become Kashmir
overnight or even in generations
possibly
then most likely retain a lot of their
own customs and have their own views and
their own music even and yet we pretend
that the opposite in Reverse is not very
interesting not going to have any
implications implications and not have
any consequences it's all going to keep
going on I just don't think it will I
think it's very obvious that it won't I
think there's a massive amount of
evidence some of which only some of
which I put in the book that says it'll
just be very different and a lot of
people say it'll be very different great
some people say it'll be very different
that's the problem but I have very
little respect or time for people who
think it's just all gonna keep being the
same there'll be good things not be bad
things I'm very willing to talk about
both but if everyone else only talks
about the good I can't help myself from
talking about some of the bad it feels
like a lot of people are feeling the
same sort of disconnect at the moment
what do you make of that yes I mean I
think that the disconnect you point to
the disconnect I've tried to write about
is when people become aware that they
are coming apart from the source of what
got them to where they are or to put it
another way
that you become aware that your soaring
off the branch of the tree that you're
sitting on doesn't necessarily mean it's
fatal but it's it's an instinct that a
lot of people have and I think has been
going on for a long time
more than a century and yes I've tried
to write about it because I think it's
something that doesn't get written about
very much I said somewhere that it's
we're living in an era where maybe one
of the first times in human history or
serving one of the first times we know
of where there is no overarching
explanation for what we're doing and
that's a big thing to miss it's a big
thing to ignore and maybe it's
inevitable that people wouldn't spend
much time thinking about it publicly
because there's an awful lot of
questions that come in the wake of that
one and I think you've said something
like this before that some of the
criticisms of strange death of Europe
focused on the immigration issue but
very few of them focused on your central
point yes I it went away it was a
disappointment to me when his book came
out that I was just very struck there
basically two major issues in the book
one is I mean to sort of make it crude
one is about them as it were people
coming in to Western societies and the
other is the US as it were what is the
Western society already and I was just
very struck that the such criticism of
that as there was focused solely on the
first part of that and that that's
slightly disappointed in me in fact it
greatly disappointed me because it
suggested that the second part the
diagnosis of the liberal West's current
situation may well be right or even more
right than I thought because nobody even
bothered to counter it I mean over
various reasons why that might be the
case the most charitable would be that
people would rather deal with what they
think of as being the more more
inflammatory issue not that I think
either issue is particularly
inflammatory but that is where you go
for the the most
difficult part as they would see it and
I think they're wrong on that because I
think the immigration but isn't the
difficult part of it I think the
difficult part of it is yes bit is what
do we expect of ourselves let alone what
we expected people who come and yes I'm
just amazed that almost nobody has
bothered to take any of that on it's
about half the book is a meditation on
us why we are where we are you in some
sense want them to refute that you know
that you were wrong yes very much
I'm very open for somebody coming along
and saying your apparent pessimism about
our present condition Murray is wildly
misguided let me tell you why I love
that you prefer the book to be wrong
sure sure I have no particular desire
for the worst things I diagnose and
worry about happening coming to be I
mean I think it's a it's a there are
some people who are so incredibly
narcissistic that they would rather the
world went to hell as they predicted
than they would prove wrong along the
way I as I say I'm very
I'd be very happy if there were a
philosophical refutation of what I say
about the exhaustion of modern European
in particular mankind but I haven't seen
it I don't doubt it's it's it's possible
but I'd love to see it come along but
there may be another reason for that is
there which is that again you that we've
sort of we've got into a habit of
certainly in public discussion of
talking about the hamster wheel because
it's endlessly diverting noisy fun
raucous sexy terrible hilarious tragic
within any 24-hour cycle so it's
understandable that we might get stuck
on it
and to an extent the first bit of what I
described in strange death of Europe is
a bit of that not all of that by any
means but a bit of that and the harder
thing is to is to press pause and say
where are we and engage in that
discussion just because there's so much
to distract us from having that
discussion you you you you you have to
do a whole lot of things mentally that
we're not currently very good at
preparing ourselves for to step off the
hamster wheel attractive as it is and
try to address the Cantus firmus I know
quite a lot of people who are in sort of
various progressive networks
developmental networks looking at very
open to this idea that what we are
seeing is in some sense a kind of
spiritual or theological crisis that
we've lost our moorings we don't know
where we are and they're very open to
the idea for example of seeing climate
change as a manifestation of this kind
of loss of a of a sense of the the
sacred much less so open to the idea
that Europe in in some sense is
committing suicide through this loss of
the sacred well several things firstly
I'm I don't ever go along really with
the term progressive and I think it
makes several massive errors one is a
lot of people like to call themselves
progressives and I was once told years
ago by a philosopher you should never
you should never use a term or never use
a sentence even the opposite of which
would only be used by a madman unless
there were a very large movement of
people boasting about being regressive
the use of the word progressive is it's
an uncounted form of halo polishing self
halo polishing I'm a progressive from
her life
what a nice person you must be not like
there's awful self-confessed regressives
over there yeah so I think it it doesn't
work on a definitional sentence it also
doesn't work because sort of it it
pushes this TV logical version of
history where we're always surging
forward to more and more write some more
and more improvement and so on and I
think I know why there's an attraction
to that I just think it's something
which even if it's so deeply embedded in
the hardware now of people in societies
like ours should be pushed back against
at least a bit I mean of course you can
save it things progress but you also
have to put great big butts in along the
way say that great argument over the
over whether or not the 20th century
constituted progress and you show all
the ways in which it did but you've got
two great big butts in the form of the
two world wars and those are massive
butts and I can I can think of smaller
examples of the same today so so the
first thing is that it may be that
progressives are dreaming and living a
dream that's not itself based on very
much other than some kind of optimistic
high so I'd say that first but the other
thing is is that there seems to me just
to be a and maps it's in what you term
the progressive mindset especially but
an unwillingness to follow ideas to
their conclusions what is one of the
most popularly heard things of our day
but I find that offensive or what you
can't say that
very rarely that's untrue very rarely I
always find an enormous relief when
somebody says that's untrue and let me
tell you why but it's it's it's quite
rare that much more
and to say that's offensive which is of
course often the case but then a lot of
the facts of life are very offensive
almost everything in life is offensive
or has a capacity to offend so it's it's
not a great way to pursue truth but then
you have to think what is even pursuing
truth a very popular past time these
days and I'm not sure it is so for all
of those reasons people don't
particularly want to the fact that
people don't really want to see things
don't really want to face up to things
is absolutely no useful criteria for
whether or not the things which they
don't want to face up to a true or not
so it may be quite the opposite the
things they don't wish to face up to the
thing things they don't wish to admit to
are probably the things most likely true
I mean the whole of life is set up in
there in a sense in this fashion isn't
it death is a pretty offensive thing and
a writer I know that you also admire
Paul Berman talks about this rationalist
naivety this this sort of sense of it's
very difficult for late late 20th
century early 21st century people to
conceive that it's possible for people
not to share their views at some
fundamental level that we're all the
same and some yes and that to me sort of
cuts to some of the core of this idea
that the very concept that people may be
telling the truth when they say that
they are motivated by religious texts
for example a lot of people feel very
resistant to that idea yeah well I think
Paul Berman who had enormous I have
enormous admiration for I don't think
he's been remotely as widely recognized
as he should have been but after 9/11
yes in the first of his major post 9/11
box terror and liberalism which made a
big splash at the time in 2003 or so
wasn't it came out Berman had been
reading them reading a lot of the
Islamist texts which I suppose he
wouldn't have read
if it hadn't been for 9/11 of course now
you have a generation going up to
university I think this year who would
have know all who were born after 9/11
just about them so we're talking about
quite quite far away history now aren't
we
but at that time when people really
didn't know anything much about the
Islamic world unless they were
specialists in it there was a big
learning curve fast learning curve Paul
Bern was one of those who threw himself
right into it and not that he had
thought widely about the nature of
Western liberalism before but he was
looking into this what this other thing
that seemed to have challenged it might
be and yes his readings of side ketubah
novels I think was was a very useful way
to demonstrate his readers as well as to
himself that that here was a
fundamentally different way of viewing
absolutely everything I mean here's the
here's the thing is so hard to realize
unless the you know the thing smashes
through your window that metaphorically
or literally that there are entirely
other ways of viewing not just what we
should do today and how we should
arrange our Diaries but everything from
the most basic acts of ablution diet
consumption behavior manners mores all
the way through to the meaning of life
love history death afterlife the
universe quite a lot is packed in there
and yes Berman was one of those who said
at a crucial moment look this what we
think is is obvious isn't obvious to a
lot of other people around the world and
and it's not obvious that it all goes
our way and that is something I'm I've
been very struck by in recent
years is the presumption of I suppose
again what you would call progressives
but the presumption of people that
history basically consists of a street
which were all walking to a glorious
place on a hill or something like that
when Francis Fukuyama is waiting for us
with open arms and that we we go up to
this high place and it the direction of
travel is so obviously attractive either
all of the things you can accrual on the
way that everybody in time joins us but
but history makes a mockery of that
because it shows us time and again
counter theories contrary events and
this isn't to say by the way that that
that for instance I had ketubah or any
of his contemporaries are the most
extraordinary refutation of what we have
in societies like the one we're sitting
in right now I think far from it I think
they're fairly easily refuted if you
would have a level playing field but at
least at the very beginning the point is
simply at berman and others made is this
is very different and also he did two
things in that book that were very
clever one to say this is very different
and also there are similarities in that
this millenarian kind of branch of islam
actually has psychological similarities
with the constant there's always a fight
between certainty and liberalism and and
it tends to result in violence yes i
have to say i'm slightly more skeptical
about some of that bit because i think
there's a tendency to I mean Berman is
the absolute best of this but there is a
tendency sometimes to read any new
historical of any event that is new to
you through the prism of what you
already know inevitably inevitably in
Britain we still tend to talk a lot
about Northern Ireland and when we talk
about conflict and you know
people around the world do not in
Britain we tend to that's because we
always what we knew in terms of
counterinsurgency and counterterrorism
and deed in conflict so there's always
that tendency we've all got it the point
is is that we all do that to some extent
and everything I'm sure I do it but but
I think in some ways it's to be resisted
and yes it's inevitable people who
experience live in the wake of 20th
century European fascism and communism
might try to understand all other
totalitarian movements millenarian
movements and others through those
lenses and they do have things in common
I mean it's sort of inevitable that
anybody once they think they can kill
them right just cause has at least the
gun in common but but beyond that I
think sometimes people stretch it I mean
there were some aspects of Islam that
are that make Islam totally unlike
anything else just as there are aspects
of fascism that make fascism totally
unlike anything else and and that isn't
to diminish observations you can make
and linkages you can make I just think
that to some extent it's more it's more
comforting to us strangely isn't it it's
more comforting to us to think we
understand a new thing that comes along
when in actual fact we may we may be
able to understand like the tiniest
corner of the tablecloth of it and you
you link a possible reason for for this
to colonial guilt mm-hmm but then guilt
in general but then you also talk about
Sweden and Sweden looks like it's
possible that native Swedes will be a
minority in their own country in the
lifetime of people living now and Sweden
had no colonies to speak of well I don't
think it's only colonialism I say that
maybe as you point out Sweden not a
colonial power
Britain was Germany did start the Second
World War Britain did not but we all
have been persuaded to share a certain
amount of German guilt seems to me you
can easily say and it's happened to me
many times in discussions and debates
you know look what we did in Europe the
Second World War you can say that in
London you can certain audience of Brits
and they can be persuaded that they had
some kind of culpability so there is a
spreading round as I see it of of guilt
which which means that the specifics and
the details become relatively
unimportant
so that Europeans from Thessalonica to
Dublin are expected to share similar
historical burdens I don't think by the
way I don't think they should I don't
think it's right and I certainly don't
think it's right doing it only ass doing
it because I think that no peoples in
history have ever been blameless I'm
interested in why we fought the idea
here so much why we are so able to be
encouraged in to this idea of guilt I
think as all sorts of religious and post
religious reasons for that I'm
interested in why or no I'm interested
in how if ever we can get out of that
guilt I cite Nietzsche on this because
Nietzsche foresaw some of this when he's
been saw that that we might retain the
Christian idea of guilt and not have the
Christian capability for absolution
which is I think the situation we are
currently in I how how do how do British
people get over colonialism at you think
most of Britain has I think this is sort
of rarified I think there are various
sadists from academia outside who think
they can persuade the British people to
feel guilty for the rest of time I don't
think they'll succeed
I think you can do that much more
successfully with the German population
life I suspect that one of the things
were already seeing and we're going to
see a lot more in the years ahead as
young Germans saying excuse me but I
didn't do it and I think we're going to
have to take an attitude towards that
we're going to have to be able to evolve
our attitudes towards it and we're going
to have to have some flexibility about
it because apart from anything else it's
not right
to tell people that they have to carry
the guilt of their great grandparents
which will be in due course but they
it's not right to tell them they should
be shouldering that till the end of time
it wouldn't be right to do it in the
same way it wouldn't be right to find
the descendants of Genghis Khan and tell
them to pay some kind of moral tax so
it's a problem this but it's it's I'm
not persuaded that it's an honest I'm
not so indeed it's an honest campaign I
think as I've often said there's a
problem of masochism in the West
particularly in Europe which may be a
kink we start to lose as we discover
there are people like to take advantage
of it but that's just that's just one
aspect of it the a guilt thing and I
think it's I think angler Merkel may
have by what she did in 2015 started to
cure a cure Europe of this it's like I
was saying and I said in Australia there
from therapy yes a thing well I think
we've done that enough might be an
instinct this starts to come up more I
think it I already hear it coming up
more I've heard it more and more since
since even since my book came out it's
only 18 months ago I think a lot of this
is I think a lot of the weather has
changed but there's also this problem
about memory in general which is we know
that a reasonable and civilized society
ought to remember it's it's you know
the former Chief Rabbi Jonathan Sacks
once said that as you know Isaiah Berlin
was once asked what it was what it meant
to be Jewish and he as a berlin said he
thought it meant to have meant to have a
sense of history and rabbis Sachs once
said no as I was almost right he said to
be Jewish means to have a sense of
memory to take that and make it not just
the Jewish thing which I think it isn't
but I think that I think civilized
people have to have a sense of memory we
know in Europe and we should know it's
not like I'm saying let's forget
anything I'm saying let's let's also
bear in mind what the correct
proportions are what what are what is a
what is a sense of history and memory
that's not just decent towards the rest
of the world but decent towards
ourselves though I think these are
questions we have to engage ourselves in
because I think people are engaging them
in their day-to-day lives all the time
and they're coming to conclusions of
their own unaided vocals Mary thank you
very much thank you
rebel wisdom is a new sense making
platform bringing together the most
rebellious and inspiring thinkers from
around the world if you're enjoying our
content then you can help us make more
by becoming a subscriber which will give
you access to a load of exclusive films
also you can then join our group zoom
cause to discuss the ideas in the films
and you can send us ideas for questions
for upcoming interviews and if you're a
regular viewer you'll know we talked a
lot about the value of embodying or
actually living out the ideas that we
talked about so that's why we run
regular events in London check out the
links on the website for more and hope
to see you soon